<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="styles/ymcaweb.xsl"?>
<ead audience="external"> 
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" dateencoding="iso8601" countryencoding="iso3166-1" relatedencoding="Dublin Core"> 
	 <eadid mainagencycode="MnU" countrycode="us" publicid="-//University of Minnesota, Twin Cities::YMCA Archives//TEXT us::MnU::yusa0004a.xml::Armed Services Records//EN">yusa0004a</eadid>
	 
	 <filedesc> 
		<titlestmt> 
		  <titleproper encodinganalog="Title">YMCA ARMED SERVICES DEPARTMENT:
			 </titleproper> 
		  <subtitle>An Inventory of Its Records</subtitle> 
		  <author encodinganalog="Contributor">Finding aid prepared by Lara D.
			 Friedman~Shedlov.</author> 
		</titlestmt> 
		<publicationstmt> 
		  <publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">University of Minnesota
			 Libraries</publisher> 
		  <date encodinganalog="Date">2004</date> 
		  <address> 
			 <addressline>University of Minnesota Libraries</addressline> 
			 <addressline>Minneapolis, MN 55455</addressline> 
		  </address> 
		</publicationstmt> 
	 </filedesc> 
	 <profiledesc> 
		<creation>EAD encoding by Lara D. Friedman~Shedlov, 
		  <date>2004.</date> </creation> 
		<langusage> <language encodinganalog="Language" langcode="eng">English</language> </langusage> 
	 </profiledesc> 
  </eadheader> 
  <archdesc type="inventory" level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC"> 
	 <did id="a1"> 
		<head>OVERVIEW OF THE COLLECTION</head> 
		<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">University of
		  Minnesota. <subarea>Kautz Family YMCA Archives.  [ymca]</subarea></repository> 
		<origination label="Creator:"> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="110">National Board of the Young Men's
			 Christian Associations. Armed Services Dept.</corpname> </origination> 
		<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Armed Services
		  records.</unittitle> 
		<unitdate label="Date:" encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive" normal="YYYY/YYYY">1863-1987.</unitdate> 
		<unitid label="Collection Number:" encodinganalog="099" countrycode="us" repositorycode="MnU">Y.USA.4</unitid> 
		<abstract label="Abstract:">Historical data, correspondence, reports,
		  memoranda, articles, newspapers, pamphlets, photographs, scrapbooks, and other
		  records documenting the YMCA's work serving the armed forces community from the
		  time of the Civil War through the present.</abstract> 
		<physdesc label="Quantity:" encodinganalog="300"><extent>267 cu. ft. (485
		  boxes).</extent></physdesc> 
		<physloc label="Location:">See Detailed Description section for box
		  listing.</physloc> <langmaterial><language>English</language></langmaterial> 
	 </did> 
	 <bioghist encodinganalog="545"> 
		<head altrender="history" id="a2h">HISTORY OF YMCA ARMED SERVICES
		  WORK</head> 
		<p>Work by the YMCA on behalf of individuals serving in the armed forces
		  began during the Civil War and has continued to the present day. What began as
		  a war emergency service was later to become an integral and continuing part of
		  the YMCA's total ministry.</p> 
		<p>Established in London, the Young Men's Christian Association came into
		  being in 1844 expressly for young men who were flocking to the city, whose home
		  and religious ties had been broken by the Industrial Revolution, and whose way
		  of living tended to be "careless and immoral" due to the fierce temptations of
		  the modern city. In less than a decade, the YMCA had spread throughout England
		  to the Continent, and in 1851, to Canada and the United States where it took
		  root in widely distant cities. Providing services to the young men in the armed
		  forces was a natural extension of the work already underway by the YMCA. </p> 
		<p>The earliest YMCA work with the armed services was a small peacetime
		  effort on board a naval training ship in Portsmouth, Virginia. Historian C.
		  Howard Hopkins notes that in 1856 the YMCA's Portsmouth Association, with the
		  government's endorsement, placed books in the ship's library and later received
		  permission to hold meetings. Similar services were initiated by the Boston
		  Association in 1859. </p> 
		<p> The YMCA's broader volunteer service to the Armed Forces, however,
		  dates from April 1861, when a handful of YMCA volunteers sought to assist
		  soldiers and sailors. This initial group aided the soldiers in the encampments
		  where they were stationed temporarily on their way to the front. Later, growing
		  numbers of volunteers accompanied the soldiers to the battlefields. Starting
		  with the small "army committee" set up by the New York Association to extend
		  preaching services, individual religious visitation, and publications to
		  soldiers stationed outside New York City, the work soon grew to a cooperative
		  venture by 15 northern associations which formed the Christian Commission.
		  Following its appointment in November, 1861, the Commission moved quickly to
		  organize on a national scale. Its first meeting was held December 11 in
		  Washington and included a conference with President Lincoln and the securing of
		  endorsements form the Secretary of War and the Secretary of the Navy. During
		  its four years of operation, the Commission recruited 5,000 volunteer
		  "delegates" who served in every theater of the war. This was the nation's first
		  large-scale civilian volunteer service corps. </p> 
		<p>Relief agencies such as the Red Cross had not yet been created, and
		  the military chaplaincy was in its infancy. Therefore, volunteers were
		  recruited from many fields, serving as surgeons, nurses, chaplains and
		  chaplains' assistants. Others distributed emergency medical supplies, food and
		  clothing. They served on the battleground with horse-drawn canteens, built and
		  operated special-diet kitchens in hospitals, brought books and prefabricated
		  chapels to soldiers and sailors, taught enlisted men how to read and write,
		  maintained a hotel for soldiers on furlough and provided free meals. YMCA
		  prisoner-of-war work — undertaken on a massive scale later during World Wars I
		  and II — began during the Civil War, when the U.S. Christian Commission
		  ministered to Confederate soldiers in northern prisons and sent supplies to
		  Union soldiers in Confederate prisons. Throughout the Civil War, the Commission
		  distributed more than 100,000 cases of food, clothing and medical supplies, and
		  12 million books, magazines and pamphlets. Its volunteer delegates wrote more
		  than 90,000 letters for the sick and wounded, and distributed $1,000 a week in
		  postage for the soldiers' use. To get supplies to the delegates, the Commission
		  created 111 YMCA Army Committees as auxiliary units.</p> 
		<p>In the three decades of peace following the Civil War, the YMCA
		  movement continued its services to soldiers and sailors, generally in state
		  militia camps. Through its Militia Camp Program, the YMCA established the
		  nation's first recreational, sports and counseling services for military
		  personnel. In 1889, the YMCA established its first permanent Army YMCA, Fort
		  Monroe, Virginia.</p> 
		<p> The YMCA's tradition of "following the flag" abroad began in the
		  Spanish-American War, when YMCA volunteers were dispatched to Cuba, Puerto Rico
		  and the Philippines. So quickly did the YMCA act that its supplies were in Cuba
		  and the Philippines before those of the Army. Teddy Roosevelt's Rough Riders
		  wrote their early dispatches on YMCA stationery, and troops in the Philippines
		  used YMCA medical supplies.</p> 
		<p>This work for soldiers and sailors was so highly regarded that the
		  YMCA's central body, in 1898, established a permanent Army and Navy Committee,
		  resulting in a rapidly expanding peacetime development. Within five months
		  after the establishment of a permanent department to serve the Armed Forces,
		  the YMCA began constructing large, well-equipped buildings to serve the
		  military. The first was the Brooklyn, N.Y., Navy YMCA, opened in February 1899.
		  Soon, YMCA Army and Navy buildings were around the world.</p> 
		<p>In the years before World War I, the YMCA movement developed the type
		  of building and mobile equipment later used during the conflict in Europe. When
		  the United States entered the war in 1917, the YMCA had developed the know-how,
		  skill and experience to launch a massive program of morale and welfare services
		  for the military — both at home and overseas. Its services were offered to the
		  government, and President Woodrow Wilson quickly accepted them. Never in
		  history had an organization brought aid to so many men, over such wide
		  geographic areas and under such adverse conditions, as did the YMCA during the
		  first World War. According to Gen. John J. Pershing, the YMCA conducted 90
		  percent of the welfare work among American Forces in Europe during the war.</p>
		
		<p>Several innovative projects created by the YMCA during WWI were
		  destined to become institutionalized: 1) Overseas entertainment for the troops,
		  which would be carried on by the United Services Organizations (USO), an
		  organization which the YMCA would help create 20 years later. 2) Overseas
		  "exchanges" for the convenience of the troops, which was continued by the
		  services. 3) Educational scholarships for veterans, which would give rise to
		  the GI Bill. 4) The concept of R &amp; R for battle-weary personnel, which
		  would become routine in future conflicts.</p> 
		<p>Following WWI, the YMCA was the only civilian organization with an
		  extensive, nationwide peacetime program for serviceman. In these years, a large
		  investment was made in Army and Navy buildings and equipment and an extension
		  of services to meet the needs of military personnel.</p> 
		<p>After the German invasion of Poland in 1939 and the subsequent
		  build-up of America defense forces, the YMCA prepared for another national
		  mobilization, coordinating its work with military leaders. To better manage a
		  large volunteer effort, in February 1941 the YMCA joined five other national
		  voluntary organizations — the YWCA, the National Catholic Community Service,
		  the Jewish Welfare Board, the Salvation Army, and the National Travelers Aid
		  Association — to create the United Service Organizations for National Defense,
		  or USO.</p> 
		<p>As the largest participating organization, the YMCA operated 25
		  percent of the 464 agency-designated USO centers in the United States; and, at
		  its war-time peak, directed a professional staff of 1,022 people, 30 percent of
		  all USO personnel. The YMCA served members of the Armed Forces through both the
		  USO centers and its network of community Associations in cities and towns
		  nationwide.</p> 
		<p>Following the disestablishment of the USO on Dec. 31, 1947, the YMCA's
		  Army and Navy Department moved immediately to fill the ensuing gap in social
		  services to the Armed Forces. In 1948, its name changed to the YMCA Armed
		  Services Department to conform to the newly organized Defense Department. The
		  YMCA Armed Services Department assumed responsibility for 26 branches operated
		  by the USO. It established work overseas where it owned property and where
		  needs were critical needs, including services on Guam and recreational programs
		  in 19 port cities of the Mediterranean area for the Sixth Fleet.</p> 
		<p>To meet the increased demands for support during the Korean War, the
		  Associated Services reactivated the USO in January 1951. Once again, without
		  interruption of programs, the YMCA became USO's major operating agency. This
		  role continued through the Vietnam conflict and into the 1970s.</p> 
		<p>In the mid-'70s, however, the YMCA's National Board of Directors
		  determined that its work with the USO had been successfully completed and that
		  it should resume delivering its unique direct services to the military within
		  its own organization. The establishment of an all-volunteer Armed Forces after
		  the Vietnam conflict brought new demands to organizations serving young
		  military people. It was necessary to keep up with changing social patterns and
		  expectations of young people. Also, the number of young families in the
		  military was increasing and YMCA programs had to meet these new needs.</p> 
		<p>Following the YMCA's decision to focus on direct services, the USO
		  asked the YMCA to assume responsibility for 12 USO centers in the United
		  States. The YMCA accepted the challenge and added these units to the Armed
		  Services YMCA network on January 1, 1977.</p> 
		<p>On January 1, 1984, following a two-year organizational review, the
		  YMCA's Armed Services Department was reorganized as the Armed Services YMCA
		  (ASYMCA) of the USA and chartered as a National Member Association of the
		  National Council of YMCAs of the USA. The major philosophical reasoning behind
		  this action was to shift direct programming activities from the National
		  Headquarters to a local member association. This new organizational structure
		  helped clarify its role and provided for greater flexibility in responding to
		  the needs of military leaders. In 1986, the ASYMCA National Headquarters moved
		  to the Washington, D.C., area to better access military leadership. The YMCA
		  continues to serve the military community through its network of Armed Services
		  YMCA branches and units, and through a number of community YMCAs conducting
		  special programs for service members and military families. </p> 
		<p>Historical information was quoted in large part from the Armed
		  Services YMCA web site (http://www.asymca.org). Additional information was
		  excerpted from <emph render="italic">Serving the U.S. Armed Forces, 1861-1986:
		  The Story of the YMCA's Ministry to Military Personnel for 125 Years,</emph> by
		  Richard C. Lancaster.</p> 
	 </bioghist> 
	 <scopecontent encodinganalog="520"> 
		<head id="a3">SCOPE AND CONTENTS OF THE COLLECTION</head> 
		<p>Historical data, correspondence, reports, memoranda, articles,
		  newspapers, pamphlets, photographs, scrapbooks, and other records documenting
		  the YMCA's work serving the armed forces community from the time of the Civil
		  War through the present. The records are divided into five, separately
		  described series. Records related to YMCA welfare work during each of three
		  major armed conflicts of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries make up the
		  bulk of the collection. These include the United States Christian
		  Commission-related records representing the Civil War era, records from World
		  War I work, and United Service Organization-related records, which cover the
		  YMCAs role in founding and operating the USO during World War II. Records
		  concerning YMCA involvement in other wars, including the Spanish American,
		  Korean, and Vietnam wars, can be found in the general and administrative series
		  which also includes historical and background data; financial records;
		  conference, committee and personnel files; and other records of the Armed
		  Services Department and its predecessor and related organizational units. Also
		  included in the collection is a series of scrapbooks and photo albums,
		  primarily dating from the time of World War I. </p> 
	 </scopecontent> 
	 <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a"> 
		<head id="a4">ORGANIZATION/ARRANGEMENT OF THE RECORDS</head> 
		<p>These documents are organized into the following separately cataloged
		  series:</p> 
		<list> 
		  <item>General Administrative Records</item> 
		  <item>United States Christian Commission-Related Records</item> 
		  <item>World War I-Related Records</item> 
		  <item>United Service Organization-Related Records</item> 
		  <item>Scrapbooks and Photo Albums</item> 
		</list> 
	 </arrangement> <descgrp> 
	 <head>ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION</head> 
	 <userestrict encodinganalog="540"> 
		<head>Use of Materials:</head> 
		<p>This collection is protected by the Copyright Law of the United States
		  (Title 17, U.S. Code). It is the user's responsibility to verify copyright,
		  ownership, and to obtain all the necessary permissions prior to the
		  reproduction, publication, or other use of any portion of these materials.</p> 
	 </userestrict> 
	 <prefercite> 
		<head>Preferred Citation:</head> 
		<p>Correct forms of citation are given for each series in the individual
		  finding aids. </p> 
		<p><emph render="italic">See the Chicago Manual of Style for additional
		  examples.</emph></p> 
	 </prefercite> 
	 <processinfo> 
		<head>Processing Information:</head> 
		<p>Catalog Record ID number: 4342462</p> 
	 </processinfo></descgrp> 
	 <dsc type="combined"> 
		<head id="a9"> DESCRIPTION OF THE COLLECTION SERIES</head> 
		<p>Note to Researchers: Please see the separate inventories for the
		  individual series listed below for more detailed information on the contents of
		  each box.</p> 
		<c01 level="series"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>[Y.USA.4-4] </unitid> 
			 <unittitle>General Administrative Records, </unittitle> 
			 <unitdate type="inclusive">1863-1987. </unitdate> 
		  </did> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Records documenting the administration of the YMCA's Army and Navy
				Department, later known as the Armed Services Department, which worked to meet
				the recreational, spiritual, educational, and other welfare needs of
				individuals serving in or associated with the United States armed services.
				Records date from the era of the Civil War through the late 1980s, particularly
				during the period from the time of the first world war through the Korean war,
				and include histories and other background information, correspondence,
				reports, financial data, personnel records, and other material. 
				<extref href="yusa0004x4.xml">&gt;&gt; Go to the complete inventory
				  </extref></p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 level="series"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>[Y.USA.4-3] </unitid> 
			 <unittitle>United States Christian Commission-Related Records,
				</unittitle> 
			 <unitdate type="inclusive">1881-1976. </unitdate> 
		  </did> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Published reports, facsimiles of commissions and correspondence,
				publications, histories, and other background material on the United States
				Christian Commission, documenting the earliest YMCA-sponsored work with the
				armed services, which developed in response to the Civil War. 
				<extref href="yusa0004x3.xml">&gt;&gt; Go to the complete inventory
				  </extref></p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 level="series"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>[Y.USA.4-1] </unitid> 
			 <unittitle>World War I-Related Records, </unittitle> 
			 <unitdate type="inclusive">1910-1970. </unitdate> 
		  </did> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Minutes, correspondence, publicity bulletins, training manuals,
				reports, newspapers, and other records of major YMCA administrative bodies
				which provided services to the military forces in the United States and abroad
				during World War I, including the National War Work Council and its
				subcommittees; the United War Work Campaign, a joint campaign of seven American
				welfare organizations, including the YMCA; the Army Educational Commission; and
				the AEF YMCA. Subjects documented include educational initiatives,
				transportation, work by women, and work in the area of physical fitness and
				recreation, as well as a significant amount of material on the YMCA's prisoner
				of war work. Also included this series are materials relating to the post-war
				investigations of the YMCA's work and to the military build-up on the Mexican
				border in 1916. 
				<extref href="yusa0004x1.xml">&gt;&gt; Go to the complete inventory
				  </extref></p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 level="series"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>[Y.USA.4-2] </unitid> 
			 <unittitle>United Service Organization-Related Records, </unittitle> 
			 <unitdate type="inclusive">1932-1980. </unitdate> 
		  </did> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>Administrative files, club histories, and other records
				documenting the YMCA's involvement with the USO, which was formed by the YMCA
				and five other civilian agencies to provide religious, recreational, welfare,
				and educational activities for men and women in the armed forces and in the
				defense industries during World War II. Materials in this series include club
				histories of both Army/Navy and industrial USOs, administrative files,
				information on associated organizations, miscellaneous records of individual
				USO clubs, and print materials, as well as publications and other material from
				the five other organizations that comprised the USO, particularly the National
				Jewish Welfare Board, the National Catholic Community Service and the Salvation
				Army. 
				<extref href="yusa0004x2.xml">&gt;&gt; Go to the complete inventory
				  </extref></p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		</c01> 
		<c01 level="series"> 
		  <did> 
			 <unitid>[Y.USA.4-5] </unitid> 
			 <unittitle>Scrapbooks and Photo Albums, </unittitle> 
			 <unitdate type="inclusive">1863-1981. </unitdate> 
		  </did> 
		  <scopecontent> 
			 <p>The series of scrapbooks and photo albums provide a visual
				overview of the work of the Army and Navy Department and the Armed Services
				Department, especially during World War I. Subjects include the Armed
				Expeditionary Forces in Koblenz, Germany, work in Russia, women workers, and
				canteens. Also documented is Mexican Border work in the 1910s, as well as work
				in prisoner and resettlement camps in Europe during the World War II era. Armed
				services work in the Far East is represented by a series of photo albums from
				the Chefoo, China Naval YMCA, dating from the 1920s-1930s. 
				<extref href="yusa0004x5.xml">&gt;&gt; Go to the complete inventory
				  </extref></p> 
		  </scopecontent> 
		</c01> 
	 </dsc> 
	 <relatedmaterial> 
		<head id="a5">RELATED MATERIALS</head> 
		<p>Photographs of armed services work are available in the Kautz Family
		  YMCA Archives photograph collection.</p> 
	 </relatedmaterial> 
	 <otherfindaid> 
		<head id="a6">OTHER FINDING AIDS</head> 
		<p>This inventory contains a summary description of each of the series
		  comprising the collection. Detailed narrative descriptions and box contents
		  lists for each of the several major sections into which the records are divided
		  are available as separate documents. </p> 
	 </otherfindaid> 
	 <controlaccess> 
		<head id="a7">INDEX TERMS</head> 
		<p>This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog
		  of the University of Minnesota Libraries. Researchers desiring materials about
		  related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these
		  headings.</p> 
		<controlaccess> 
		  <head>Topics:</head> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Korean War, 1950-1953 -- War work --
			 Young Men's Christian Associations. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Prisoners of war. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Soldiers -- Recreation. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Spanish-American War, 1898 -- War work --
			 Young Men's Christian Associations. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975 -- War
			 work -- Young Men's Christian Associations. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young
			 Men's Christian Associations. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Young
			 Men's Christian Associations. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Young Men's Christian Associations --
			 Administration. </subject> 
		  <subject encodinganalog="650">Young Men's Christian Associations --
			 Buildings. </subject> 
		</controlaccess> 
		<controlaccess> 
		  <head>Places:</head> 
		  <geogname encodinganalog="651">United States -- Armed Forces --
			 Military life. </geogname> 
		  <geogname encodinganalog="651">United States -- Armed Forces --
			 Religious life. </geogname> 
		  <geogname encodinganalog="651">United States -- Armed Forces -- Service
			 clubs. </geogname> 
		  <geogname encodinganalog="651">United States -- Armed Forces -- Songs
			 and music. </geogname> 
		  <geogname encodinganalog="651">United States -- History -- Civil War,
			 1861-1865 -- War work -- Young Men's Christian Associations. </geogname> 
		</controlaccess> 
		<controlaccess> 
		  <head>Organizations:</head> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">National Board of the Young Men's
			 Christian Associations. Army and Navy Dept. </corpname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">National War Work Council, Y.M.C.A. of
			 the United States. </corpname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">United Service Organizations (U.S.).
			 </corpname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">United States. Army. </corpname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">United States. Navy. </corpname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">United War Work Campaign, Inc.
			 </corpname> 
		  <corpname encodinganalog="710">Young Men's Christian Associations of
			 North America. International Committee. Army and Navy Dept. </corpname> 
		</controlaccess> 
		<controlaccess encodinganalog="655"> 
		  <head>Types of Documents:</head> 
		  <genreform>Photographs. </genreform> 
		  <genreform>Scrapbooks.</genreform> 
		</controlaccess> 
	 </controlaccess> 
  </archdesc> 
</ead>
